<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Installation</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Navigation Top">
            <a href="./index.html">&lt;&lt;Back to the Start Page</a>
            or

            <a href="./usingGeneral.html">On to the General Users Guide&gt;&gt;</a>
        </section>

        <section name="General information">
            This page covers the general installation and integration process of Apache MyFaces Extension scripting
            1.0.2 or earlier,it does not go into the details of the configuration.
            As of ext-script 1.0.3 a number of legacy dependencies are dropped for easier maintainability such as

            <ul>
                <li>Support for Java 5 and earlier</li>
                <li>Support for MyFaces 1.2.x</li>
                <li>Support for Servlet 2.5 and earlier</li>
            </ul>

            If you need to use Ext-Scripting with one of those configurations stick to 1.0.2.

            The section covers the setup via download or custom build. If you need configuration detail info
            or info on how to setup your ide correctly please follow the links in the navigation to
            the correct section.

        </section>


        <section name="Setup overview">
            <subsection name="General Setup Information" >
             <p>

                Ext-Scripting has a complete appendix list over all configuration and setup options
                for a quick overview please visit the following links. If you need detailed
                setup information, then read further on.
             </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Links">
                <p>
                    <ul><a href="./setupSteps.html">Appendix: Configuration Setup Steps</a> </ul>
                    <ul><a href="./exampleconfig102.html">Appendix: Example Configurations for 1.0.2 or earlier</a>
                    </ul>
                    <ul><a href="./configentries102.html">Appendix: List of Configuration Options for 1.02 or earlier</a> </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>


        <section name="Checklist">
            <p>

            For a short checklist of setup steps please follow <b><a href="./setupSteps.html"> this link</a></b>. For a detailed
                setup guide, please continue reading.
            </p>
        </section>


        <section name="Download">
            <p>
                With version 1.0 Ext-Scripting provides all necessary artifacts
                as download artifacts to get quickly started.
                A kickstart project is provided which can be used as shell for your own
                projects.
            </p>
            <p>
                For Download information please visit the <a href="./download.html"> download  page</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Once you downloaded the necessary artifacts please check the <a href="#Manual_Setup">manual setup section</a> of this document.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Checkout and Build">
            <p>
                While Ext-Scripting is already in beta stage, the best way to get started
                is probably to checkout and build ext-scripting yourself from the latest codebase.
                All other installation steps will have this step as prerequisite if you want to
                use the latest codebase instead of one of the beta releases!
                First you have to check out the latest codebase from

                <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/myfaces/extensions/scripting/trunk">
                    http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/myfaces/extensions/scripting/trunk
                </a>

                via a subversion client.
            </p>
            <p>
                Make sure you have following requirements fulfilled before checking out:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A valid Subversion client</li>
                <li>Java 5 or higher</li>
                <li>Maven 2.0.9 or higher</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                After checkout, a full build can be obtained from the root directory of your checkout via <b>mvn
                clean install</b>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Once finished, a valid build is installed, which can be used further on. Additionally you can find
                two blueprint projects which you can use as starting points for your own projects under
                <b>&lt;checkoutDir&gt;/examples</b>
                , which can be started via<b>mvn jetty:run-exploded</b>.
                The now generated files either can be used to be included in a maven install or be included manually
                (please go to the next section for detailed setup instructions)

            </p>

        </section>

        <section name="Setup of Ext-Scripting">

            <subsection name="Requirements">
                <p>
                    Before setting up Ext-Scripting for your project make sure following requirements are met.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>JAVA_HOME points towards a valid Java SDK (JRE is not sufficient)</li>
                    <li>You know how to create and deploy a web application within your preferred setup (command line,
                        ide)
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Setup">
                <p>
                    While one of the aims of Ext-Scripting was to enable an easy setup, for now it was not entirely
                    possible for now to get a plug and play configuration. Several configuration steps have to be
                    performed.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>A valid
                        <b>MyFaces</b>
                        installation has to be present
                    </li>
                    <li>Ext-Scripting and its dependencies has to be added to the MyFaces installation</li>
                    <li>The paths to the scripts have to be present (see also below)</li>
                </ul>

            </subsection>


            <subsection name="Preparations via Apache Maven 2">
                <p>The easiest way once Extension scripting is compiled is probably a setup via Apache Maven 2
                </p>
                <p>
                    Depending on your configuration and preferred JDK version you can add following entries to your
                    Maven pom.xml to enable Ext-Scripting
                </p>

                <p/>
                <h4>MyFaces 1.2.8+</h4>
                <source><![CDATA[
     <dependency>
        <groupId>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting</groupId>
        <artifactId>extscript-myfaces12-bundle</artifactId>
        <version>1.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
     </dependency>]]></source>

                <h4>MyFaces 2.+</h4>
                <source><![CDATA[
     <dependency>
        <groupId>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting</groupId>
        <artifactId>extscript-myfaces20-bundle</artifactId>
        <version>1.0-SNAPSHOT</version>
     </dependency>]]></source>
            </subsection>

    
            <subsection name="Manual Setup">
                <p>If you do not like Maven or you prefer a manual setup, Ext-Scripting provides convenient meta bundles.
                    A manual setup
                    comes down to the task of adding the appropriate meta bundle (extscript-myfaces12-bundle or
                    extscript-myfaces20-bundle)
                    to your WEB-INF/lib directory and adding a groovy-all.jar as additional dependency.
                </p>
                <p>you can obtain both jars after the build from:
                    <ul>
                        <li>&lt;yourbuilderoot&gt;/extscript-bundles/extscript-myfaces12-bundle/target/extscript-myfaces12-bundle-1.0-SNAPSHOT.jar</li>
                        <li>&lt;yourbuilderoot&gt;/extscript-bundles/extscript-myfaces20-bundle/target/extscript-myfaces20-bundle-1.0-SNAPSHOT.jar</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>After having done that you are ready to setup the rest of the Ext-Scripting configuration manually as
                    described in the section blow
                </p>
            </subsection>


            <subsection name="Preparing the Necessary web.xml Entries">
                <h4>First Step</h4>
                <p>To enable Ext-Scripting you also have to add several entries to your web.xml file.</p>

                <p>First a context param has to be set which attaches the Ext-Scripting plugins to MyFaces</p>
                <source><![CDATA[
     <context-param>
        <description>
            Enables our scripting engine support plugins
        </description>
        <param-name>org.apache.myfaces.FACES_INIT_PLUGINS</param-name>
        <param-value>
            org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.servlet.StartupServletContextPluginChainLoader
        </param-value>
     </context-param>]]></source>
                <h4>Second Step</h4>
                <p>Add Ext-Scriptings servlet filter to your servlet configuration</p>
                <source><![CDATA[
    <filter>
        <filter-name>scriptingFilter</filter-name>
        <filter-class>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.servlet.ScriptingServletFilter</filter-class>
    </filter>
    <filter-mapping>
        <filter-name>scriptingFilter</filter-name>
        <url-pattern>/*.jsf</url-pattern>
        <dispatcher>REQUEST</dispatcher>
        <dispatcher>FORWARD</dispatcher>
        <dispatcher>INCLUDE</dispatcher>
        <dispatcher>ERROR</dispatcher>
    </filter-mapping>]]></source>
                <p>The init parameter and the servlet filter
                    <b>MUST</b>
                    be set otherwise Ext-Scripting will not be enabled!
                </p>
                <p> For the filter pattern you can use every pattern which enables your web pages,
                the standard cases are, either <b>*.jsf</b> or <b>/faces/*</b>
                Note you <b>must</b> use the same pattern as described in the configuration
                part of your Faces Servlet.</p>
                <h4>Additional Optional Steps</h4>
                <p>Ext-Scripting exposes a number configuration parameters which can be set via context parameters in
                    your web.xml
                </p>

                <h4>Adjust the web.xml Root source paths.</h4>
                <p>Since the goal of Ext-Scripting is to provide scriptability to a running web application, it has to
                    know where to find the sources. For this, a default location has been chosen
                    according to the standards set by the Mojarra Groovy Extension.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The location looks like:
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
     <webapp>/WEB-INF/groovy                    
                ]]></source>
                <p>
                    as root location for Groovy files
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
     <webapp>/WEB-INF/java
                ]]></source>
                <p>
                    as root location for java files.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Following image displays the default locations:
                    <img src="images/ext-default-file.jpg"/>
                </p>
                <p>However in a normal development scenario, it is often undesirable to have the files located in a
                    deployment location, and a pointer mechanism towards the actual source locations would be more
                    desirable.

                    To provide such a mechanism, Ext-Scripting allows two optional web.xml context parameters, which
                    allow the rerouting of source locations of the supported languages!
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
    <context-param>
        <description>Additional comma separated loader paths to allow direct editing on the sources directory instead
            of the deployment dir
        </description>
        <param-name>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.groovy.LOADER_PATHS</param-name>
        <param-value>
           <some project path>/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/groovy
        </param-value>
    </context-param>
    <context-param>
        <description>Additional comma separated loader paths to allow direct editing on the sources directory instead
            of the deployment dir
        </description>
        <param-name>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.java.LOADER_PATHS</param-name>
        <param-value>
            <some project path>/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/java
        </param-value>
    </context-param>
                ]]></source>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.groovy.LOADER_PATHS</b>
                        can be a comma separated list of paths which point to the actual Groovy sources.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>org.apache.myfaces.extensions.scripting.java.LOADER_PATHS</b>
                        does the same for Java sources..
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="Navigation Bottom">
            <a href="./index.html">&lt;&lt;Back to the Start Page</a>
            or

            <a href="./usingGeneral.html">On to the General Users Guide&gt;&gt;</a>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
        